{"tossups": [{"question": "This man hoped to be remembered as \"the acutest, astutest, and archest enemy of southern slavery.\" This man died after collapsing while shouting \"No!\" about a bill to honor Mexican-American War veterans. This Congressman convinced colleagues to use the funds from James Smithson's trust to create a scientific institution. James Madison appointed this man the first ever U.S. Minister to Russia. He was the first President to serve in Congress after his term of office ended and assumed his highest office thanks to a \"corrupt bargain\" with Henry Clay. For the point, name this son of a former President who became President in 1825.", "answer": "<b><u>J</u></b>ohn <b><u>Q</u></b>uincy <b><u>Adams</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Adams</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \u201cJohn Adams\u201d]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "The crime of smuggling this commodity out of the country was called \"owling.\" The Duke of Sutherland ordered some \"clearances\" to expand production of this good. The Cockayne Project attempted to ban the export of this commodity, which was traded by the Merchants of the Staple. This commodity was soaked in stale urine by fullers. The seat of the Speaker of the House of Lords is a sack filled with this good, which was frequently exported to Flanders. For the point, name this commodity which is treated with carding and obtained from sheep.", "answer": "<b><u>wool</u></b> [or <b><u>tweed</u></b>; prompt on \"sheep\"; prompt on \"cloth\" or similar answers]  {III}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "Because of this event, the height of flimsy structures called <em>insulae</em> was restricted. People blamed for this event were used as human torches during dinner parties. After this event, the architects Severus and Celer were hired to build the Domus Aurea, or Golden House. The Pisonian conspiracy was formed following this event. A man who blamed this event on secret communities of Christians supposedly sang about Troy and played his lyre while it occurred. For the point, name this event that destroyed large parts of Rome during Nero's reign.", "answer": "Great <b><u>Fire</u></b> of <b><u>Rome</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "This team had a super fan named Karl Ehrhardt who held up a sign reading \"There Are No Words\" after it won a title. This team won a game partially thanks to a \"shoe polish\" incident in which Cleon Jones claimed to have been hit on the foot. In its first championship series, Ron Swoboda and Tommie Agee made brilliant catches. Nolan Ryan won his only World Series with this team, whose star pitchers included Jerry Koosman and Tom Seaver. For the point, name this team which won the 1969 World Series, a \"Miracle\" team that had lost 120 games back in its first year of 1962.", "answer": "New York <b><u>Mets</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>New York</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "The wealthy Spring Valley neighborhood of Washington, D.C. is built over chloride compounds of this element buried by the U.S. Army after World War I. Peasants in Styria swallowed balls of this element to increase libido, inspiring a few Victorian copycats. A central atom of this element occurs in Paul Ehrlich's \"magic bullet\" drug, the first chemical treatment for syphilis. Its anion, when bonded to gallium, forms a common semiconductor in consumer electronics. The Marsh test detects this element. For the point, name this extremely toxic metalloid used in Victorian England as an over-the-counter rat poison.", "answer": "<b><u>arsenic</u></b> [or <b><u>As</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "An assuredly fabricated solution to this mystery involves the New York banker Irene Bolam. A 1966 Fred Goerner book about this mystery quoted Naval Commander John Pillsbury. Chester Nimitz was quoted as saying the answer to this mystery involved people being captured by the Japanese in the Marshall Islands. Outlandish solutions to it involve participants working as spies for Franklin Roosevelt before World War II. This mystery involves what happened to Fred Noonan and a Lockheed Model 10 Electra in the Pacific Ocean in 1937. For the point, name this mystery about the disappearance of a female aviator.", "answer": "The disappearance of Amelia <b><u>Earhart</u></b> [accept the \u201cdisappearance of Fred <b><u>Noonan</u> </b>until mentioned\u201d]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "This king\u2019s second wife was the subject of the Encomium <em>Emmae Reginae</em>. The Archbishop of Canterbury \u00c6lfheah was pelted to death with bones during the reign of this king (*), who arranged an uneasy alliance with Thorkell the Tall. This king arose to the throne after his mother \u00c6lfthryth allegedly arranged the murder of his predecessor in Corfe Castle. During his reign, Byrhtnoth lost to Viking invaders at the Battle of Maldon. He ordered the killing of all Danes in England in the St. Brice\u2019s Day massacre, and was succeeded by Sweyn Forkbeard. For the point, name this English king whose epithet comes from an Old English word meaning \u201cbad counsel.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Aethelred II</u></b> [or <b><u>Aethelred the Unready</u></b>; accept <b><u>Cnut</u></b> the Great until (*)]  {III}", "metadata": "CKM"}, {"question": "A member of this group was shot and killed while assisting Leila Khaled in hijacking El Al Flight 219 in 1970. This group founded the newspaper <em>El Nuevo Diario</em> after the publication <em>La</em> <em>Prensa</em> criticized them. Despite this group's campaigns to improve literacy, the country it rules still has the lowest literacy rate in Central America. A \"National Opposition Union\" against this group was led by Violeta Chamorro. This group overthrew the Somoza dynasty in 1979, and their members include Daniel Ortega. For the point, name this leftist party in Nicaragua.", "answer": "<b><u>Sandinista</u></b> National Liberation Front [or <b><u>FSLN</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "A member of this group also served on the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles at the same time and later became President of the LDS in 1985. This group was called \"eight millionaires and a plumber.\" As he prepared to join this group, a man known as \"Engine Charlie\" said \"for years I thought what was good for our country was good for General Motors.\" This was the first group to feature a head of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. Its most notable member was a staunch anti-Communist, whose brother Allen headed the CIA. For the point, name this group which featured John Foster Dulles as Secretary of State.", "answer": "The <b><u>Cabinet</u></b> of Dwight <b><u>Eisenhower</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "This man is the subject of several works by Ernest Meissonier. Apsley House is home to a sculpture of this man holding a staff and a miniature figure of Nike standing on an orb. He looks to the right at a man with the number \u201c32\u201d on his hat in a painting showing him surrounded by plague victims in Jaffa. The names \u201cKarolus Magnus\u201d and \u201cHannibal\u201d appear on rocks at the bottom of a painting of this man on a rearing white horse. The Duke of Hamilton commissioned a painting of this man leaning on an Empire style desk at his study in the Tuileries. For the point, name this man, whose coronation was depicted in a Jacques-Louis David painting.", "answer": "<b><u>Napoleon</u><u>Bonaparte</u></b> [accept either underlined; or <b><u>Napoleon</u></b> I]  {III}", "metadata": "CKM"}, {"question": "This man explained the theory of tides in his essay Discourse on the Tides. This man\u2019s last book <em>The Two Sciences</em>, introduces his paradox about infinite sets.He included sketches of the moon in his book <em>The Starry Messenger.</em> He legendarily said \u201ceppur si muove,\u201d or \u201cand yet it moves\u201d after his book <em>Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems</em> was banned by the Catholic Church. He also discovered Callisto, Io, Ganymede, and Europa. For the point, name this Italian scientist who championed the Copernican model of the solar system.", "answer": "<b><u>Galileo</u><u>Galilei</u></b> [accept either name]  {III}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "Translations of this man's work by Harriet Martineau popularized his views in England. This man envisioned a set of worldwide temples modeled on Catholicism without God in his plans for a secular \"Religion of Humanity.\" The motto \"Ordem e progreso,\" on Brazil's flag, is translated from the writing of this man, who wrote that humanity progressed from the \"metaphysical\" to the \"theological\" stage as part of his Law of Three Stages. For the point, name this French founder of the pro-science philosophy of positivism, who coined the terms \"altruism\" and \"sociology\".", "answer": "Auguste <b><u>Comte</u></b> [or Isidore Auguste Marie Fran\u00e7ois Xavier <b><u>Comte</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "This man told Governor William Claiborne that he was \"the stray sheep, wishing to return.\" This man was killed in an attack on the ship <em>General Santander</em> and previously served as the manager of the secret trades on the island of Barataria. He eventually began capturing slave ships from his colony of Campeche on Galveston Island. This man, with his older brother, Pierre, met with Andrew Jackson in December 1814 and offered his assistance for a battle which ended in January the following year. For the point, name this French pirate who was pardoned for his service at the Battle of New Orleans.", "answer": "Jean <b><u>Lafitte</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Kachak movement in this province was suppressed following the death of Azem Galica. In 1981, student protests in this province led to the ouster of Mahmut Bakalli. Along with Vojvodina (<b>pr. voy-VOH-dee-nuh</b>), this province had its autonomy rescinded in 1989. The failure of the Rambouillet (<b>pr. ram-boo-yay</b>) Conference led to NATO bombing campaigns against one side in this province's civil war, which pitted its ethnic Albanian majority against the forces of Slobodan Milosevic. For the point, name this former Yugoslavian province that declared independence from Serbia in 2008.", "answer": "<b><u>Kosovo</u></b> [or <b><u>Kosova</u></b>; or Republic of <b><u>Kosovo</u></b>; or Autonomous Province of <b><u>Kosovo</u> </b>and Metohija; or Socialist Autonomous Province of <b><u>Kosovo</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "One member of this movement was executed for his supposed role in the \"Conspiracy of the Ladder\" and wrote under the pseudonym Placido. Carlos Manuel de Cespedes issued the \"Grito de Yara\" before starting a ten-year war attempting to achieve this movement's aims. This movement gained traction in the United States due to Valeriano Weyler's attempts to combat it, which earned Weyler the nickname \"The Butcher\". For the point, Jose Marti was the best-known member of what movement that attempted to liberate a Caribbean island from Spanish rule?", "answer": "<b><u>Cuban independence</u></b> movement [prompt on <b><u>Cuba</u></b> before \"aims\" is read]  {III}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "This rebellion lost power after Yang Xiuqing's execution after he attempted to wrest control from its leader. This rebellion ended after forces under Zeng Guofan took Nanjing, which had been renamed Tianjing by this rebellion. Frederick Townsend Ward took part in fighting against this rebellion. This rebellion suffered defeats at the hands of \"Chinese\" Gordon and the Ever-Victorious Army. The leader of this rebellion joined the God Worshippers' Society and believed himself to be the younger brother of Jesus Christ. For the point, a \"Heavenly Kingdom\" was set up by Hong Xiuquan, the leader of what rebellion against the Qing dynasty?", "answer": "<b><u>Taiping</u></b> Rebellion  {III}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "The first book of reporter Randy Shilts was a biography of this man, his close friend. This man's \"Hope Speech\" denounced the Briggs Initiative, which targeted certain public school teachers. His one-time intern was UNITE HERE activist Cleve Jones. The White Night riots broke out after this man's killer successfully used the \"Twinkie defense\" at his trial. Known as the \"Mayor of Castro Street,\" he was, along with George Moscone, killed by former city supervisor Dan White in 1978. For the point, name this member of the San Francisco Board of Supervisors, the first openly gay person to be elected in California.", "answer": "Harvey <b><u>Milk</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "A work by one of these people hails Richard I as the \u201cfather of valor\u201d and describes his death as \u201ca very cruel event.\u201d A form of rhyming debate called a <em>tenso</em> was invented by one of these people named Cercamon. Dancers and jugglers called <em>jongleurs</em> often accompanied these people. These people composed biographical songs called <em>vida</em> and dirges called <em>planh.</em> Eleanor of Aquitaine patronized several of these people, and her grandfather William IX was one of them. Bernard de Ventadour and Arnaut Daniel were prominent examples of these people. For the point, name these wandering poets of the Middle Ages who composed songs in Occitan.", "answer": "<b><u>troubadour</u></b>s [do not accept \"trouveres\"]  {III}", "metadata": "CKM"}, {"question": "This colony ceded the Oblong to its western neighbor in 1683. A border dispute with this state\u2019s northern neighbor was resolved in 1801, creating the Southwick Jog. It lost the Pennamite Wars, a dispute over control of the Wyoming Valley in present-day Pennsylvania. This state set aside the Firelands for victims of British arson in towns such as Danbury and New London. It ceded the remainder of its trans-Appalachian claims in 1800, giving up control of land that is now northeastern Ohio. For the point, the Western Reserve was claimed by what New England state?", "answer": "<b><u>Connecticut</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "This party expelled its left-wing 79 Group in 1982. Winnie Ewing was this party\u2019s first Member of Parliament. It rescinded its opposition to NATO in 2012, and its current platform calls for relocation of the Trident missile system. This party has since 2007 formed the government in Holyrood and is currently headed by Nicola Sturgeon. Its long-time leader Alex Salmond stepped down after its failure to defeat the Better Together campaign in a 2014 referendum. For the point, what party is working to make the northern third of Great Britain an independent country?", "answer": "<b><u>Scottish National Party</u></b> [or <b><u>SNP</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "This series includes an entry addressed to Guy Carleton asking him to \"give up your murderer.\" The author of this series discussed being at Fort Lee at the land by the Hackensack. This series claimed that \"tyranny, like hell, is not easily conquered\" and that \"the summer soldier and the sunshine patriot\" would shrink away. The first entry in this series begins with the line \"these are the times that try men's souls\" and was read aloud before the Battle of Trenton. For the point, name this pamphlet series written by Thomas Paine to encourage Americans during the Revolutionary War.", "answer": "<em>The American</em> <em><b><u>Crisis</u></b></em> [or <em>The</em> <em><b><u>Crisis</u></b></em>]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "A 1990 performance of this album on Potsdamer Platz featured flutist James Galway during \u201cGoodbye Blue Sky.\u201dIts narrator laments \u201cI\u2019ve got fading roots\u201d in \u201cNobody Home\u201d before reminiscing about wartime singer Vera Lynn. According to its primary songwriter, its central track is the anti-war song \u201cBring The Boys Back Home.\u201d At the start of this concept album, which was adapted into a film with animation by Gerald Scarfe, the protagonist's father dies as a World War II pilot, an incident drawn from Roger Waters\u2019 life which puts the first bricks into its title structure. For the point, in what Pink Floyd double album does a chorus of children proclaim \u201cwe don\u2019t need no education\u201d?", "answer": "<em><b><u>The Wall</u></b></em> {III}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "Bunny Greenhouse claimed this company engaged in some of \"the most blatant and improper\" abuse she had ever seen. A former head of this company was hit with corruption charges in 2010 regarding the building of a plant on Bonny Island in Nigeria. This company's one-time subsidiary, Kellogg, Brown, and Root, had an employee, Jamie Jones, claim to have been gang raped at Camp Hope. This company's seven billion dollar contract leading up to the 2003 Iraq War raised suspicion since Vice President Dick Cheney was its former CEO. For the point, name this Houston based oilfield service company.", "answer": "<b><u>Halliburton</u></b> Company [accept <b><u>Kellogg, Brown, and Root</u></b> until mentioned; accept <b><u>KBR</u></b> until \u201cKellogg\u201d]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "This many statues made up the Monument to the Eponymous Heroes. A board of this many men were appointed to create the Twelve Tables. The Alexandrian Canon is a list of this many great Attic orators. In the Roman army, mutinous troops were punished by being divided into groups of this size, each of which would have to beat one of their members to death. The strategoi were a group of this many generals elected every year in Athens. Cleisthenes organized Athenian society into this many phyles, or tribes. For the point, how many years was the Trojan War believed to have lasted?", "answer": "<b><u>Ten</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "A 2010 court ruling about this city divided a holy plot of land into thirds, giving one-third to the Nimrohi Akhara sect. The legendary slayer of the demon Indrajit came from this city, in a tale in which a pair of sandals was left on its throne. A 1992 bombing of the Babri mosque in this city was linked to the nationalist party BJP. In a poem revered by Hindus, a prince exiled from this city for fourteen years defeats the ten-headed <em>rakshasa</em> Ravana to rescue his wife Sita. For the point, name this site of religious tension in contemporary India, regarded as the birthplace of Vishnu's avatar Rama.", "answer": "<b><u>Ayodhya</u></b>, India  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "One senator from this state was called the \u201cSenator from Formosa\u201d for his support of Chiang Kai-Shek. That person from this state became the youngest ever Majority leader following the death of Robert Taft. Another person from this state won an election against Helen Douglas for Senator using a \u201cPink Sheet.\u201d That person from this state gained fame by breaking the Alger Hiss case while a member of the House Un-American Activities Committee and would later become President of the United States. For the point, name this home state of William Knowland and Richard Nixon.", "answer": "<b><u>California</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "A poem named for this location describes \u201cbrutish necessity wiping its hands upon the napkin of a dirty cause.\u201d A poem named for this place, which is dedicated to the Sicilian King Robert of Naples, features historical events such as the death of Mago Barcid. A postcolonial poem named for this place describes \u201cKikuyu, quick as flies\u201d and was written by Derek Walcott. This place also titles a Renaissance epic which recounts Scipio\u2019s victory at the Battle of Zama. For the point, a poem by Petrarch is named for what continent?", "answer": "<b><u>Africa</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "Since antiquity, mines in the Badakhshan region of Central Asia have by far produced the largest supplies of this good. Cutting this inorganic substance, which the ancient Romans valued as an aphrodisiac, produces an odor from the trisulfide radical anion that also gives it its color. Glass and this solid material make up the non-gold stripes of Tutankhamun's burial mask. During the Renaissance, artists such as Titian crushed this material to make the pigment known as ultramarine. For the point, name this deep blue gemstone.", "answer": "<b><u>lapis lazuli</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "Pauline Sabin founded a group to support this cause after hearing a speaker claim to represent \"the women of the United States.\" This cause was supported by the New York based \"Molly Pitcher Club.\" The Cullen-Harrison Act accomplished one goal of this cause, which was backed by the Women's Moderation Union. John D. Rockefeller Jr. eventually endorsed this cause because of the \"unprecedented\" increase in crime. It was supported by people who felt the Volstead Act had simply resulted in bootlegging. For the point, name this goal accomplished by the 21st Amendment.", "answer": "<b><u>repealing Prohibition</u></b> [or <b><u>ending Prohibition</u></b>; accept <b><u>passing the 21st</u></b> <b><u>Amendment</u></b> until mentioned; do not accept \u201cProhibition\u201d or \u201ctemperance\u201d]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "William Waller and Philip Stapleton were two of eleven members suspended from this body after being accused of treason.The Vote of No Address was repealed by this body after the battle of Preston, and the Earls of Essex, Manchester and Warwick were forced to step down from military commands after it passed the Self-Denying Ordinance. This body was assembled after a rout at Newburn led to the capture of Newcastle. Many of its members walked out after Thomas Pride arrested several other members, leaving the \"Rump\" parliament. For the point, name this legislative body under Charles I which lasted for a whopping eight years.", "answer": "<b><u>Long</u></b> Parliament [prompt on <b><u>Parliament</u></b>, prompt on <b><u>Rump</u></b> Parliament]  {III}", "metadata": "VP"}, {"question": "The Brady Hotel in this city was founded by KKK leader W. Tate Brady. A jury ruled this city's Police Chief John Gustafson was both derelict of duty and corrupt. Inflammatory headlines in its newspapers caused a mob to threaten the life of shoeshine boy Dick Rowland. An incident in this city began after the reported Memorial Day \"rape\" of a female elevator operator. The Greenwood District in this city, which was known as the \"Black Wall Street,\" was destroyed in an event that featured World War I biplanes dropping firebombs on black homes. For the point, name Oklahoma city that was the site of a massive 1921 race riot.", "answer": "<b><u>Tulsa</u></b>, Oklahoma  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "For a time, this institution was replaced by the Jovians and Herculians. This group held an auction that was won by Didius Julianus during the Year of the Five Emperors. A member of this institution who was strangled and thrown down the Gemonian Stairs schemed to seduce Livilla as part of his plan to marry into the Julio-Claudian dynasty. Septimius Severus dissolved this institution and replaced it with members of his Pannonian Legions. Augustus reorganized this institution into nine cohorts of 1000 men each, and only allowed three cohorts in the capital at any given time. Sejanus was a powerful prefect of this institution. For the point, name these bodyguards of Roman emperors.", "answer": "<b><u>Praetorian</u></b> Guard [or <b><u>Praetorian</u></b>s]  {III}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "The ship Blessing of the Bay was built for this man. This man quarreled with his deputy and successor in office, Thomas Dudley. This person claimed that \"in all times\" God made \"some\u2026be rich, some poor\" in a speech saying people should be \"knit together by the bond of love.\" While on the ship <em>Arbella</em>, this man used imagery from the Sermon on the Mount in a speech.This man delivered the sermon <em>A Modell of Christian Charity</em> in which he stressed that colonists were forming a \"city upon a hill.\" For the point, name this Puritan who served twelve terms as Governor of the Massachusetts Bay Colony.", "answer": "John <b><u>Winthrop</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "In March 2015, Operation Decisive Storm was launched in this country. During an uprising in this country, a battle was fought over control of Zinjibar. Fighting often occurred near the Darul al Hadeeth school in the Siege of Dammaj in this country. In a 2011 revolution here, Ali Abdullah Saleh stepped down from power. Since 2012, the president of this country has been Abd Rabbuh Mansur Hadi, who has received military aid from northern neighbor Saudi Arabia against a Zaidist rebel group. For the point, name this country in which Houthi rebels recently took control of the capital Sana'a.", "answer": "<b><u>Yemen</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "An article about this event has a title translated as \"Shame on you, clowns!\" Allegations about this event blamed Russian conductor Igor Markevitch, while conspiracy theories have implicated members of the Masonic lodge Propaganda 2. A s\u00e9ance led the police during it to raid the town of Gradoli. After this event, a corpse was found in the trunk of a Renault 4 parked on the via Caetani. This event culminated in the Red Brigades killing the president of the Christian Democracy Party. For the point, name this 1978 event in which a former Italian Prime Minister was kidnapped and murdered.", "answer": "The <b><u>kidnapping</u></b> of Aldo <b><u>Moro</u></b> [or the <b><u>murder</u></b> of Aldo Moro; accept synonyms for \u201ckidnapping\u201d or \u201cmurder\u201d; prompt on <b><u>Years of Lead</u></b> and <b><u>Anni di piombo</u></b>]; accept just \u201cAldo <b><u>Moro</u></b> after \u201ckidnapped\u201d.  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "Andrew Szydlo wrote about a man who partook in this activity in his book <em>WaterWhich</em> <em>Does Not Wet Hands</em>.Practitioners of this activity include Michael Sendivogius, and some of its practitioners coined the term \u201cmagnum opus\u201d. Edward Kelley claimed to have learnt this activity from the archangel Uriel. Rubedo and Nigredo, or the reddening and blackening of substances, is used by this discipline to transmute rocks into the fabled philosopher\u2019s stone. For the point, name this medieval discipline whose practitioners sought to turn lead into gold.", "answer": "<b><u>alchemy</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "Ike"}, {"question": "This bill was sometimes named after Pennsylvania senator Joseph Grundy. Thomas Lamont of J.P. Morgan called this bill \"asinine\" and said it \"intensified nationalism all over the world.\" This bill was co-sponsored by a Republican Senator from Utah who was the subject of a four year debate about whether his Mormon apostle status rendered him ineligible to serve. Paul Douglas, Irving Fisher, and over a thousand other economists signed a petition asking Herbert Hoover to veto this legislation, which made U.S. imports decrease 66 percent. For the point, name this 1930 law that set tariff rates to record levels.", "answer": "<b><u>Smoot-Hawley</u></b> Tariff [or <b><u>Hawley-Smoot</u></b> Tariff; accept <b><u>Tariff</u></b> Act of <b><u>1930</u></b> until \u201c1930\u201d]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "A C Major piece in this form by Joseph Haydn was subtitled \u201cIn Time of War.\u201d The first complete example of this musical form was written by Guillaume de Machaut, and over forty \u201cparody\u201d examples of this form are based on the song \u201cL\u2019homme arme.\u201d One of these pieces supposedly prevented the Council of Trent from banning polyphony. Giovanni Palestrina wrote one of them for Pope Marcellus, and its final section is usually the \u201cAgnus Dei.\u201d For the point, \u201cKyrie\u201d and \u201cGloria\u201d are sections of what musical setting of the Catholic liturgy?", "answer": "<b><u>mass</u></b>es [or <b><u>Missa</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "Banker John Riordan saved people from this event by claiming hundreds as dependents. A photograph of the lead-up to this event taken by Hubert van Es depicts numerous people at the Pittman Apartment building. The build-up to this event used the playing of \"White Christmas\" as a signal for American personnel to move into position. Shortly before it took place, Operation Frequent Wind evacuated 7,000 people, including many American civilians. After this event, a city was renamed \"Ho Chi Minh City.\" For the point, name this April 30, 1975, event in which the capital of South Vietnam was captured.", "answer": "The <b><u>fall of Saigon</u></b> [or the <b><u>capture of Saigon</u></b>; or the <b><u>evacuation of Saigon</u></b>; accept \u201c<b><u>Ho Chi Minh</u></b> City\u201d for \u201cSaigon\u201d until mentioned]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "This animal may have been domesticated following a papal decree that it could be eaten during Lent. During his Mexican exile, Leon Trotsky raised chickens and these animals. In the 1950's, Paul Armand-Delille accidentally killed off over ninety percent of this animal's European population by causing a myxomatosis outbreak. They aren't dingoes, but in the 1900's, a series of fences was built to keep these animals out of Western Australia. For the point, since it was brought to Victoria in 1859, what herbivore has wreaked havoc on Australia's ecosystem?", "answer": "European <b><u>rabbit</u></b> [or <em><b><u>O</u></b>ryctlagus</em> <em><b><u>cuniculus</u></b></em>]  {III}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "This institution was rigorously modernized by President William Jewett Tucker. This institution was named after the title of William Legge in an attempt to get him to donate money, which he did not do. This place was founded by Eleazar Wheelock, the former tutor of a Mohegan named Samson Occom. A tearful speech with the line \"a small college\u2026and yet there are those who love it\" was delivered about it by alumnus Daniel Webster, in a case involving treasurer William Woodward and the New Hampshire legislature. For the point, what Ivy League school was the subject of an 1819 Supreme Court case?", "answer": "<b><u>Dartmouth</u></b> College [or <b><u>Dartmouth</u></b> University]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "Following an assassination attempt on a foreign viceroy of this country, 30,000 of its residents were massacred on Yekatit 12. This country was the site of the largely decorational March of the Iron Will. A leader of this country shot himself on Easter Monday after imprisoning several British subjects at Magdala. Robert Napier led an expedition against this country's emperor, Tewodros II. Although this country successfully repelled invaders at the Battle of Adowa, it fell to Italian forces in 1936. For the point, name this country once known as Abyssinia and ruled by Haile Selassie.", "answer": "<b><u>Ethiopia</u></b> [accept <b><u>Abyssinia</u></b> until it is read]  {III}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "This work was loaned to the Oval Office for several months in 2011. Four people in this painting wear yellow armbands and are depicted only from the shoulders down. The wall in the background of this painting has been defaced with graffiti and a splattered tomato, and this painting\u2019s subject has a ruler and pencils in hand. First published in <em>Look</em>, it depicts a 1960 scene in which six-year-old Ruby Bridges is on her way to William Frantz Public School. For the point, in what Norman Rockwell painting do four U.S. Marshals enforce <em>Brown v. Board of</em> <em>Education</em>?", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Problem We All Live With</u></b></em>  {III}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "One son of this man enforced the Statutes of Kilkenny on the Irish. This father of Lionel of Antwerp came into conflict with the Good Parliament over the influence of his mistress, Alice Perrers, and he himself took power after defeating his mother\u2019s mistress, Roger Mortimer. This person\u2019s forces won the Battle of Sluys, gaining control of the English Channel, and his greatest military success occurred when his longbow archers defeated a force of French knights at the Battle of Crecy. For the point, name this English King during the Hundred Years War, the father of Edward the Black Prince and son of Edward II.", "answer": "<b><u>Edward III</u></b> Plantagenet  {III}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "In 2004, the person serving in this role was a former National Endowment for the Humanities head who had blasted the National History Standards in 1994 for being too \"politically correct.\" In 1978, the person serving in this role was a culture buff known as \u201cJoan of Art.\u201d In 1995, duties of this role were carried out by a woman who earlier co-founded the Parents Music Resource Center to demand warning labels on \"objectionable\" music. That woman has since separated from her husband, the Nobel winning author of <em>An Inconvenient Truth</em>. For the point, name this role whose duties were carried out by Lynne Cheney and Tipper Gore.", "answer": "<b><u>Second Lady</u></b> of the United States [or <b><u>wife/spouse</u></b> of the <b><u>Vice-President</u></b> of the United States]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "The territorial expansion of one of these two countries was opposed by the other's fascist Black Dragon Society. During a visit to one of these countries with George of Greece, a future ruler of the other was struck on the face with a saber by a would-be assassin. Warships travelling from one of these countries to fight the other attacked fishermen in the Dogger Bank incident. These countries clashed at Port Arthur and Tsushima in a war which ended with the Treaty of Portsmouth. For the point, name these two countries, a European power and a Asian island nation which fought a 1904 war.", "answer": "<b><u>Russia</u></b> AND <b><u>Japan</u></b> [accept in either order; or <b><u>Rossiya</u></b> for \"Russia\"; or <b><u>Nippon</u></b> for \"Japan\"; or <b><u>Russo-Japanese</u></b> War]  {III}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "The success of this series led to a lawsuit from Harold Courlander, who said it was based on his 1967 novel. This series led to a follow-up program where Marlon Brando played Nazi George Lincoln Rockwell. In this series, Ben Vereen played cockfighting expert \"Chicken George.\" The eighth episode of this series remains the third most watched fictional television program of all time. Historians argue its first part, set in The Gambia, led viewers to incorrectly believe white slave traders abducted the most slaves in Africa. For the point, name this 1977 miniseries based on an Alex Haley novel about Kunta Kinte.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Roots</u></b></em> [or <em><b><u>Roots</u></b>: The Saga of an American Family</em>]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "This religious denomination performs baptisms by doing three full submersions in a natural body of water. This denomination's leader Avvakum was burnt at the stake a few years before one of their monasteries self-immolated in the face of troops crossing the frozen Lake Onega. These people, who were on the losing end of a conflict called the <em>Raskol,</em> were accused of supporting Empress Sophia when the <em>streltsy</em> revolted. This denomination retained a two-fingered sign of the cross even after the reforms of Patriarch Nikon. For the point, name these people suppressed in the 1600s for refusing to modernize along with the Russian Orthodox Church.", "answer": "<b><u>Old Believer</u></b>s [or <b><u>stradovery</u></b>; prompt on Russian <b><u>Orthodox</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "An attempt at this activity in Mexico was led by Jose Gutierrez and Augustus Magee. A participant in this activity lost the Second Battle of Rivas after ill-advisedly attempting to take over a steamboat company owned by Cornelius Vanderbilt. A secret society of \"knights\" planned to use this activity to create a Golden Circle. For engaging in this activity, Narciso Lopez and William Walker were both executed. For the point, name this practice of invading Latin American territory in which pro-slavery adventurers participated.", "answer": "<b><u>filibuster</u></b>ing [prompt on \"piracy\"; prompt on answers like \"invading Cuba\", \"invading Nicaragua\", \"invading Mexico\", \"invading Latin America\", etc]  {III}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "During this period, the first military code of law of the country, the Goseibai Shikimoku, was adopted. During this period, Hojo Yoshitoki came into conflict with Cloistered Emperor Go-Toba in the Jokyu war. During this period, there were two Mongol invasions, and the money spent preparing for a third invasion led to its downfall. This period was ended when Go-Daigo successfully rebelled in the Kemmu restoration, and the first leader of this shogunate was Minamoto no Yoritomo. For the point, name this Japanese shogunate which followed the Heian period, the first Japanese shogunate.", "answer": "<b><u>Kamakura</u></b> shogunate  {III}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "This man said that the middle class needed to stand up to \"environmental extremists who put birds\" ahead of families. In 1992, this man claimed 38% of the New Hampshire G.O.P. primary vote to frighten incumbent George Bush. He described a \"religious war\u2026for the soul of America\" at the Republican National Convention of that year. In one election, numerous Palm Beach County voters probably voted for this man using a confusing \"butterfly ballot\" instead of Al Gore. For the point, name this conservative who ran on the Reform Party ticket in 2000.", "answer": "Patrick \u201cPat\u201d <b><u>Buchanan</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "During this event, armed forces besieged the offices of a newspaper known as <em>Vorwarts</em>. The catalyst for this event was the dismissal of police chief Emil Eichhorn, and Gustav Noske ultimately gave the orders for troops to move in from Potsdam and shoot anyone who came near them. During this event, a woman was shot by First Lieutenant Vogel and thrown into the Landwehr Canal. It was named for a Marxist group led by Rosa Luxemburg. This event ended with mass arrests and killings perpetrated by Friedrich Ebert's Freikorps. For the point, name this failed uprising in January 1919 in Germany.", "answer": "<b><u>Spartacist</u></b> Uprising [or <em><b><u>s</u></b><b><u>partakusaufstand</u></b></em>; prompt on the <b><u>January Uprising</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "During this event, Pierre Cruzatte shot a man in the thigh after confusing him for an elk. Paul Allen edited a two-volume history of this event written by banker Nicholas Biddle. The leader of this event either shot himself or was murdered at an inn a few years later while on his way to demand money from the War Department. This event featured people meeting withMandan chiefs, where they encountered trapper Toussaint Charbonneau and his wife Sacagawea. For the point, name this 1804 to 1806 expedition scouting land acquired during the Louisiana Purchase.", "answer": "Meriwether <b><u>Lewis</u></b> and William <b><u>Clark</u></b> expedition [or <b><u>Corps of Discovery</u> </b>expedition]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "The site of this battle was where the first \"Kalkriese-type\" face mask was discovered. This battle was followed by a clash on the \"field of maidens,\" the Battle of Weser River. Segestes allied himself with the losers of this battle in an attempt to get revenge on the winner for marrying his daughter Thusnelda. The loss at this battle prompted a man to wander his palace shouting \"give me back my legions!\" The general Varus committed suicide after being ambushed by Arminius at this battle. For the point, name this disastrous defeat for the Roman army in a German woodland.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Teutoburg Forest</u></b> [or Battle of <b><u>Teutoburger Wald</u>] </b> {III}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "During this war, many people fled to safety at Miles Morgan's fortified house. In the last battle of this war, John Alderman shot an enemy leader. It was sparked by the murder of Christian convert John Sassamon. This conflict featured hundreds dying during the Great Swamp Fight, and the losing side's leader was killed while fleeing to Mount Hope, Rhode Island. Mary Rowlandson's captivity narrative describes this war, whose leader was also known as \"Metacomet.\" For the point, name this bloody 1670's war between New Englanders and an American Indian coalition led by a Wampanoag chief.", "answer": "King <b><u>Philip\u2019s</u></b> War [accept <b><u>Metacom</u></b>et\u2019s War until \u201cMetacomet\u201d is mentioned]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}], "bonuses": []}